<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The light of Christ, and the word of life. Cleared from the deceipts of the Deceiver, and his litterall weapons turned upon his owne head. Also the man of sin found out, who is hiding himselfe in a heape of confusion, pretending Antichrist is not yet come. Occasioned by laying open some deceipts in a booke titled, The deceiv'd and deceiving Quakers discovered; subscribed Mathew Caffin and William Jeffery, brethren in iniquitie, who are joyned to deny God, Christ, the light, and spirit, in his saints, and calls it teaching Christs spirit apart from his body, and an evill spirit, to witnesse the spirit of Christ in the saints. Set forth that the simple may see the wiles the devill hath to keepe them from the word of life, the soules salvation. / By a lover of Israels seede, called James Nayler.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E877_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206580</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865703</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865703</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168378</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89842)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168378)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 132:E877[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The light of Christ, and the word of life. Cleared from the deceipts of the Deceiver, and his litterall weapons turned upon his owne head. Also the man of sin found out, who is hiding himselfe in a heape of confusion, pretending Antichrist is not yet come. Occasioned by laying open some deceipts in a booke titled, The deceiv'd and deceiving Quakers discovered; subscribed Mathew Caffin and William Jeffery, brethren in iniquitie, who are joyned to deny God, Christ, the light, and spirit, in his saints, and calls it teaching Christs spirit apart from his body, and an evill spirit, to witnesse the spirit of Christ in the saints. Set forth that the simple may see the wiles the devill hath to keepe them from the word of life, the soules salvation. / By a lover of Israels seede, called James Nayler.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the Black-spread-Eagle, near the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 22".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Caffyn, Matthew, 1628-1714. --  Deceived, and deceiving Quakers discovered --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jeffery, William, 1616-1693. --  Antichrist made known --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Antichrist --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168378:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LIGHT OF CHRIST, AND THE WORD OF LIFE.</p>
            <p>Cleared from the Deceipts of the Deceiver, and his litterall Weapons turned upon his owne head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo the Man of ſin found out, who is hiding himſelfe in a heape of Confuſion, pret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nding Antichrist is not yet come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Occaſioned by laying open ſome Deceipts in a Booke titled, <hi>The deceived and deceiving</hi> Quakers <hi>Diſcovered;</hi> Subſcribed <hi>Mathew Caſſin</hi> and <hi>William Jeffery,</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in iniquitie, who are joyned to deny God, Chriſt, the light, and Spirit, in his Saints, and calls it teaching Chriſts Spirit apart from his body, and an evill Spirit, to witneſſe the Spirit of Chriſt in the Saints.</p>
            <p>Set forth that the Simple may ſee the wiles the Devill hath to keepe them from the word of Life, the Soules ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a lover of</hi> Iſraels <hi>ſeede, called</hi> James Nayler.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Even now there are many Antichrists, and whoſoever denyeth the Father and the Son, the ſame is he that is the lyar and the Antichrist.</hi>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abide in me and I in you, for without me you can doe nothing.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black-ſpread-Eagle, near the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168378:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168378:2"/>
            <head>THE LIGHT OF CHRIST, and the word of Life.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ATHEVV CAFFIN who to ſhew thy ſelfe amongſt the body of oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath raked up a heape of filth out of thy owne heart to caſt on the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light, adding lye to lye, ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins and ſo ends, for in thy beginning thou ſayes even now are there many Antichriſts; And in the end of thy booke thou ſay'ſt that Antichriſt will but be one ſingle man; And as is the beginning and ending, ſo is the whole bulke a lumpe of lyes, ſlanders, and Confuſions, as one would thinke the Devill himſelfe might bluſh at, As that the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſaith, and cannot but ſay that Chriſt aſcended not into heaven with that body which God raiſed from the dead, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; And that we ſay the body and blood of Chriſt is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable; That we Imagine Chriſt never dyed, That we ſay that the offering of Chriſts body to be broken and his blood to be ſhed avails not, ſo as through faith therein to ſet free from ſinne; And that we deny the holy Scriptures; And much ſuch like, which to write after thee might fill a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume; but ſeeing they are but ſlanders moſt of them caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our perſons, and that our practiſes doe every day teſtifie againſt them, ſo that none but who are willfully blind, but they may both heare and ſee contrary, and ſeeing we need looke for no other but that all manner of evill muſt be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt us without cauſe by the lyar who is that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: for his names ſake who hath called us out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, we ſhall therefore willingly receive it as great rules,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168378:3"/> till the Lord our righteouſneſſe make <hi>Eſau</hi> aſhamed at his envies. There is onely two things which as to the way of God, may prejudice ſome who are ſimple, which I ſhall lay open thy deceipts in, and for the reſt leave it to diſcover its author, and by what ſpirit he is guided, which the leaſt Child of light may eaſily Judge being nothing but a heape of ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, from the old roote ſeverally ſpoken to in other places. Thoſe two I ſhall mention is touching the light of Chriſt, and the Word, which thou denies to ſet the letter in the ſtead; which two things being cleared the whole worke falls to nothing, but falſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccuſations. The firſt is thy envie againſt the light of the world, that lighteth every man that cometh into the world. And to undervalue this thou ſayes, That falſe and erronious is that Spirit that bids men give atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to a light within, as their onely teacher; And that Chriſt did not Commend people to a teacher within; And that men are not led into all truth by a light within them; And that to ſuppoſe that God in men is their teacher, is an Error, not knowing the Scriptures; And that it is not to be found in all the Scriptures that Chriſt or any of his did coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell ignorant people to waite upon a light within them, &amp;c. And that to declare the light within is another report, and another Spirit than Chriſt and his Miniſters, and much the like thou inveighs againſt the light, ſhewing thy ſelfe utterly blind, and a Child of darkneſſe; And yet ſayeſt thou the Goſpell is hid, and the Creature loſt, where the God of this world hath blinded the minde, and yet wilt thou have no light within; And ſayeſt thou it concernes us to have our lights burning, yet denies the light within, but doth not tell people where their lights muſt burne without them, nor where their enlightened minds muſt be without them; And much ſuch darke mudd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſtuffe comes out from the waters of <hi>Babylon,</hi> too much to gather up after thee, whereby thou ſeekes to darken and undervalue the light of the world, as not to be a teacher ſufficient, that ſo Antichriſt might keepe people in blindneſſe, and ſo in their ſins. Such a worke as none was ever found in but the Devill and his Inſtruments, quite contrary to Gods Covenant, and the end of it, even the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168378:3"/> Covenant of light, in which God hath placed all his promiſes and power, yea where God himſelfe dwells, even in the light of Chriſt the true light that lighteth every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the world, which was the meſſage that the Miniſters of Chriſt was to declare, which Antichriſts Miniſters op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>And that this light is the onely leader and guide to all ſorts of people, and in all eſtates, and that without beleeving and following this there is no ſalvation, but without it all are in darkneſſe: I ſhall make it plaine by the Prophets, Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and their teſtimony of it againſt whome thou beares thy teſtimony, and the reſt of the Children of darkneſſe, even againſt that light which is the anoynting, which was typified by that pure oyle of the Tabernacle; of which the Law and the Prophets propheſied, even the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant of light, both to Jews and Gentiles; As ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 6. And in the 49. 6. God calls it a light to the Gentiles, and for ſalvation to the ends of the earth. And this thou would limit onely to ſuch as thou calls beleevers, which indeed appeares the greateſt enemies to it. And in the 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h Chapter 17. he ſaith, <hi>This light ſhall burne up as a fire the briers and thornes in his day.</hi> Alſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 3. 19, 20. And through his whole Propheſie he makes it the ſumme of his worke to foretell the Coming and beautie and power of this light, and all the reſt of the Prophets, which would be too large to mention.</p>
            <p>And <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> the greateſt of the Prophets, who came to ſee this light, he teſtifies of him what he is, and what he doth, that through him all might beleeve, whoſe whole teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony was of this light <hi>John</hi> 1. he ſaith, <hi>This is the true light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world;</hi> and calls him the <hi>Word that was in the beginning, by whom all things was made;</hi> and ſaith, <hi>in him is life, and the life was the light of men, and that this light ſhined in darkneſſe, but the darkneſſe comprehends it not.</hi> And this light thou denies and would li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to ſome perſons, who act in darkneſſe and cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it, though it ſhine in darkneſſe; wherefore ſaith the blind guide, this is another report, and another Spirit, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168378:4"/> ſuch a thing is not to be found in all the Scriptures, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee thy blind Spirit, oppoſing the living Spirit of light and life in all the Saints, both in Scriptures, and to this day. And <hi>Simeon</hi> the Prophet he teſtifies to this light, and ſaith, <hi>He is prepared before the face of all people, a light to lighten the Gentiles, and the Glory of his people Iſraell;</hi> and calls it <hi>Gods ſalvation,</hi> Luke 2. 30, 31, 32. But ſaith the falſe Prophet, and Antichriſt, this is not ſufficient alone, though it be <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raells</hi> glory and ſalvation, and the Gentiles light.</p>
            <p>And ſaith Chriſt of himſelfe, <hi>I am the light of the world, he that followes me ſhall not abide in darkneſſe, but ſhall have the light of life,</hi> John 8. 12. But ſaith Antichriſt, this light is not ſufficient of it ſelfe. And ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Take heed that the light thats in thee be not darkneſſe. The light of the body is the eye, therefore when thine eye is ſingle, the whole body is full of light, but when thy eye is evill, thy whole body is full of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; Take heed therefore that the light which is in thee be not darkneſſe.</hi> And this he ſpake to the people and the Phariſees, <hi>Luke</hi> 11. But ſaith Antichriſt, it is not to be found in all the Scriptures, that Chriſt or any of his did Counſell Ignorant people to take heed to a light within them; and ſaith the Blaſphemer, Falſe and Erronious is that Spirit that bids men attend to a light within. So the lyar and the Antichriſt is now revealeing, and there are many Antichriſts who thus oppoſe Chriſt his light and doctrine, who have the hornes of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, and dare blaſpheme God in his Temple, Calling the Spirit of Chriſt falſe and Erroneous; And ſaith that to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that God in men is their teacher, is an Error not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures; when the Scripture ſaith, <hi>You ſhall all be taught of God,</hi> John 6. 45. <hi>And know you not that yee are the Temple of the living God, as God hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walke in them:</hi> and the Temple of God is holy, whoſe Temple ye are, but ſayeſt thou for to ſuppoſe God to teach thee, is an Error, and ſo art not afraid to blaſpheme God in his Temple. And ſaith the Scripture, <hi>All thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhall be taught of the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 54. 13. <hi>And they ſhall teach no more every man his neighbour, and every man his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaying, know the Lord, for they ſhall all know me from the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168378:4"/> leaſt of them to the greateſt,</hi> Jere. 31. 34. Heb: 8. 11. But ſaith the Children of darkneſſe, where the Son of perdition ſits in the Temple of God, this is Error, who are ſtrangers to this Covenant of light, and without God in the world, who are of ſuch the Apoſtle tells on, <hi>Eph:</hi> 4. who becauſe of the blindneſſe of their hearts (through denying the light within) are alienated from the life of God, and ſo become paſt-feeling, and ſo are given to ſin and plead for it, though it be their deſtruction, for all that deny the light within are heart-blind, and ſo ſtrangers to the life And here are all you blind guids of all ſorts, enemies to the light, ſtumbling at it which is the Corner Stone, and ſo all that hate the light loves your evill deeds, and ſo plead for them while you live, and ſo the words of Chriſt is fullfilled upon you, <hi>John</hi> 3. 19, 20.</p>
            <p>And ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I am come a light into the world, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever beleeveth in me, ſhould not abide in darkneſſe,</hi> and hee exhorts the Phariſees and unbeleevers, (who beleeved the Scriptures) to beleeve in the light of the world, which <hi>John</hi> calls <hi>the true light, which ligheth every man that cometh into the world;</hi> and ſaith Chriſt, <hi>God ſo loved the world, that hee gave his onely begotten Sonne, that whoſoever beleeveth on him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life; but he that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not, is condemned already, and this is the condemnation that light is come into the world and men love darkneſſe rather than light:</hi> and this he ſpake of them that beleeved the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as you blinde guids doe now, but would not beleeve in the light of the world, as you doe now who deny Chriſt to be the light of the world, and would limit him only to be the light of Beleevers, which beleevers, when ſearched, you are found to be enemies to the light; but ſaith they that beleeve, he is a light to lighten the Gentiles, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 32. And the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that ſate in darkneſſe ſaw a great light, and to them that ſate in the Region and ſhaddow of death, light is ſprung up; <hi>Math:</hi> 4. 16. But ſaith Antichriſt, hee inlightneth none but ſuch as are inlightned already, that ſo he may keepe all in darkneſſe that are in darkneſſe; but the Children of light know that there is no other thing to inlighten them that ſit
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168378:5"/> in darkneſſe, whoſe minds the God of this world hath blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the light of Chriſt, and till then, the Goſpell is hid, and the vaile is over the heart, and all other meanes, till the eye be open is unprofitable, and it is his light alone which is that eye, and his Spirit alone, that takes away that vaile, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3. 16, 17. And that it is his Spirit alone that guides into all truth, <hi>John</hi> 16. 13. Even the ſame Spirit which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves the world of ſin, <hi>ver:</hi> 8. But ſaith Antichriſt, men are not lead into all truth by a light within, ſo by thy doctrine the Spirit of truth muſt either not be within, or elſe darkneſſe within, for ſayeſt thou men are not lead into all truth by a light within; but ſaith the Scriptures, <hi>Yee have an unction from the holy one, and yee know all things, and this anoynting abideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame anoynting teacheth you of all things,</hi> and is truth, and is no lye, and even as it hath taught you, yee ſhall abide in him, but ſaith the lyar, that ſpirit is falſe and erroneous, that bids men give attendance to the light within, as their onely teacher, when the Spirit of God ſaith, Yee need not any man to teach you, but as the ſame anoynting that abideth in you, teacheth you of all things and no lye is in it, and commands them to abide therein. And this ſpirit thou calls falſe and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious, and ſo art found that Blaſphemer againſt the Spirit of God, and an open lyar, who ſaith there is not ſuch a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as directs to a light within for the onely teacher, and though in thy Book thou ſayeſt wee muſt wraſtle againſt the Powers of darkneſſe in this world, yet art thou found in the world joyned with the Prince of the world, to wraſtle againſt the light of the world, even the ſpirituall light of Chriſt, which all the holy men of God did ever beare witneſſe too, and preached to them that was in darkneſſe, and witneſſed it to be that by which they was inlightened, even the light within, which ſhined out of darkneſſe in their hearts, which gave them the knowledge of the Glory of God, in the face of Jeſus, which was their treaſure in the earthen veſſels, which they Preached and not themſelves, that the Praiſe might be wholy of God, who had given them this light in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, wherefore they renounce the hidden things of diſhoneſty,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168378:5"/> not handling the word of God deceitfully, but by manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this truth commend themſelves to every mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the ſight of God, and not to the fleſhly wiſdome nor braine knowledge, but to the light in every mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. and they exhorted them, to have no fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the unfruitfull works of darkneſſe, but to reprove them, and ſaid all things that are reproved are made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by the light, and whatſoever doth make manifeſt is light, and this they preach for the light of Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 11, 13, 14. and doth alſo declare that the want of this light having their underſtandings darkned, and the blindneſſe of their hearts is the cauſe why men are paſt feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo given themſelves over to laſciviouſneſſe, to work all uncleaneſſe with greedineſſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 18, 19. But he ſaith the Sains have not ſo learned Chriſt, if they have heard him and been taught by him, as the truth is in Jeſus, being renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſpirit of their minds who ſometimes were darkneſs but now are light in the Lord, and ſo walk as children of the light bringing forth fruits of the Spirit in all goodneſſe righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and truth: and this light was their meſſage, which they declared to their hearers, as the way to the bloud of cleanſing; ſaith <hi>John, This is the meſſage as we have heard of him, and declare unto you, that God is light and in him is no darkneſſe at all, if we ſay we have fellowſhip with him and walk in darknes we ly &amp; do not the truth, but if we walk in the light as he is in the light we have fellowſhip one with another, and the blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us from all ſin, 1 Joh.</hi> 1. 5, 6, 7. This light they Preached, to be the way out of the world, following Chriſt who led them therein, who ſaith, <hi>I am the light of the world, no man cometh to the Father but by me,</hi> this light they preached to be the way to cleanſing by the blood of Jeſus, and this light they preached to keep out of the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of ſtumbling, and ſaid they that walk in darkneſſe know not whether they go, becauſe that darknes hath blinded their eyes, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 10, 11. And this was the end of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, which was the end of the Covenant, and the end of Chriſts coming, even to open the blind eyes, and to bring them that ſit in darkneſſe out of the Priſon houſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 7. And this was the end of the Apoſtles Miniſtry, to open their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168378:6"/> eyes and to turne them from darknes to light and ſo from the power of Satan to God, <hi>Acts</hi> 27. 18. And this eye was within them that was blind which they was to open, which the God of this world had blinded which Chriſt calls the light of the body, and therefore ſaith, <hi>Take heed that the light thats in thee be not darkneſſe,</hi> Luke 11. 34, 35. Which eye the blind guides who loveth the world and their ſin have cloſed, and their ears they have ſhut, whoſe hearts are wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en groſſe, ſo that they can neither ſee hear nor underſtand, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 15. And in this ſtate are all you blind guides, blind leaders of the blind, who can neither ſpeak nor walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law and Teſtimony becauſe ye know not the light in ye, nor can any but from that light within, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in your blindneſſe are oppoſing the light of the world, which the Law and the Prophets propheſied of, which had the Teſtimony of Jeſus which we witneſs to be the light of the world, who are come to the end of the Law and the Prophets, even the new Covenant, where the Law is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the heart, and the ſpirit of Propheſie received which is the teſtimony of Jeſus, which we knew not till that eye was opened, and therefore went along with you in your blind worſhips and ſelfe taken on performances from the letter, which gave us no life, which life we witneſſe now in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by faith in the light of Chriſt, and his commands in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is life and power for obedience to the faith, in the light it is ſeen and accepted, in which light we ſee you and your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours which are without, not in the light and ſpirit, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny you, and your ſparks, your kindling, your literall Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſelfe righteouſneſſe, and all your brick making, who are in the Aegyptian darkneſſe, enemies to the light of Iſrael and its ſeed; And you we ſee to be enemies to <hi>Zions</hi> Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as you are enemies to the light of the world, both in your ſelves and others.</p>
            <p>And this I ſay further to thee, and the reſt of thy dark generation, That all your boaſt of Religion and knowledge in the letter, will not bring you to God, without the light of Chriſt, nor can any one that is in ignorance come to know the way to life but by the light of the world, and untill man
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168378:6"/> be led thereby he cannot come out of his darkneſſe, even with that light that reproves the world, and manifeſt your evill deeds muſt he be led; though the beaſts of the field, who know not what liberty the Sons of God have in his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, calls this a Spirit of bondage, which is bondage to the beaſtly nature, but is freedome to the Sons and Seed of God, which the love of God is too who loves purity, but hates ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou and the reſt of you would confine the light of Chriſt onely to ſuch who are enlightned already, I ſay who muſt enlighten the reſt? is there ſome other light to be preached before him? is not he the author as well as the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher? who are enlightned indeed knowes this that he is the light in the times of darkneſſe, and there is none beſides him, and that he giveth life to all who receive his light and follow it, but thoſe that rebell againſt the light knows not the wayes thereof, nor abides in the paths thereof, <hi>Job</hi> 34. 13. There in that Chapter thou maiſt read thy ſelfe, and thy way, and work: Is this the end of your talking of the Spirit, and is it now become an error to ſay its ſufficient to teach and guide out of darkneſſe, and is it ſome carnall thing that muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the mind and guide the heart of man, which is in darkneſſe, ſuch a doctrine as this was never preached by any of Chriſts Miniſters, whoſe meſſage was to preach Chriſt all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient in all, to work the whole work in fallen man both to light and life, which if thy doctrine be not quite contrary let the work in thy book teſtifie.</p>
            <p>Thy ſecond thing that thou wouldſt prove is, that the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Scripture is the word of God, and ſo the Rule and touchſtone to judge ſpirits with, and that by which the world muſt be judged, and much ſuch like that belongs to God and his Spirit alone in Chriſt Jeſus, wouldſt thou in oppoſition thereto aſcribe to the letter, not knowing what the word Rule and Judge is; And this to prove thou addes a great heap of confuſions and contradictions, but cannot find one Scripture that ſaith the letter is the word.</p>
            <p>But thou inſtances that place <hi>Marke</hi> 7. 12, 13. which hath relation to the 5 Commandement, and with a deal of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168378:7"/> confidence thou affirmes that Chriſt calls the letter the word in this place, becauſe he ſaith they make the word of God of none effect by their traditions, ſo thou haſt proved the letter of that Commandement to be thy word, but in thy 24 page having forgot thy word thou overthrows it againe, and ſayes the Apoſtle calls that the letter of the Law which killeth, and the miniſtration of death written and engraven in ſtones, by which no fleſh ſhall be juſtified, of which letter the Apoſtles was not Miniſters of.</p>
            <p>So by thy proofe thy word is that by which no fleſh ſhall be juſtified, but is the letter that killeth, and miniſtration of death, of which words the Apoſtles was not Miniſters, and in thy 39 page thou ſayes it is done away, ſo thou haſt loſt thy word, and ſuch like wild confuſed drunken ſtuffe, thou haſt to prove the letter the word, wherein thou haſt rightly proved thy word to be that which the Apoſtles was no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of nor by it ſhall any be juſtified, and this is thy main pillar which falls thus on thy own head, but where the light of Chriſt is denyed, the blind muſt needs ſtumble, though at noon day; but they that have the word know that the word they made voyd by their traditions, was what God had written in their hearts, of which the outward was a figure, <hi>Iſa. 51. 7. Pſal. 119. 11. Mat.</hi> 13. 15.</p>
            <p>Another proof thou brings, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 41. which ſaith they that gladly received <hi>Peters</hi> word were baptized; in which thou haſt proved the letter not to be the word, for they that <hi>Peter</hi> preached to had the letter before they received <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> word, which word was Chriſt, of which the letter te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies.</p>
            <p>Such like as theſe are all the reſt of thy proofes, many groſſe lies mixt amongſt them, not worth the while to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or repeat after thee. As thou art not aſhamed in thy 25 page to lye againſt the Apoſtles words, ſaying they were Miniſters of the letter, which the Apoſtle plainly denies, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 6. As indeed is the moſt of thy work in thy book to oppoſe plaine Scripture, and contradict thy ſelfe. As for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance:</p>
            <p>Saith <hi>Paul Gal.</hi> 1. When it pleaſed the Father to reveal
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168378:7"/> his Son in me, that I might preach him, I went <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sayeſt thou page 26. The Apoſtles went forth teſtifying the Lord Jeſus not come within them.</p>
            <p>Saith Chriſt the Spirit of truth, When he is come, he ſhall teſtifie of me.</p>
            <p>Sayeſt thou page 33. Which Spirit the Saints receiving did not declare him to be their onely inheritance.</p>
            <p>Saith Chriſt, The Spirit of truth ſhall guide you into all truth, <hi>John</hi> 16. 13.</p>
            <p>Sayeſt thou page 15. Men are not led into all truth by a light within.</p>
            <p>Saith Chriſt, Take heed that the light that is in thee be not darkneſſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Sayeſt thou, Falſe and erronious is that Spirit that bids men give attendance to a light within.</p>
            <p>Saith Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 5. 25. The houre is coming, and now is, when the dead ſhall hear the voyce of the Son of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sayeſt thou page 45. Not come and now is.</p>
            <p>Saith the Apoſtle 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6. God who commanded light to ſhine out of darkneſſe, hath ſhined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſpeaks of ſome whom the God of this world had blinded their minds, leaſt the light of the glorious Goſpell ſhould ſhine unto them.</p>
            <p>Sayeſt thou page 8. (as to the ſame thing) not from a teacher within, but from the Apoſtles; who plainly affirme that they were to give the light of the knowledge of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, ſo putting the Apoſtles inſtead of God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying them, ſays they affirme it, when the Apoſtle ſaith, God gives it, and not they.</p>
            <p>And thus thou ſhewes thy ſelfe all along to be that man of ſin, that old gainſayer, who oppoſeth thy ſelfe againſt the truth of the Scriptures, and yet would have the letter thereof to be the word which thou canſt thus turne and wreſt againſt the truth, but the word thou knows not which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be wreſted, altered nor changed; nor canſt thou prove the letter to be it, though many crooked wayes thou takes to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168378:8"/> doe it, but its hard to take the letter to prove againſt the word, which doth teſtifie of the word from whence it came.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing thou canſt not prove the letter to be the word, I ſhall prove that the letter is not the word, and the letter it ſelfe ſhall witneſſe with me therein.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That which one may have and not have the word, is not the word; but one may have the letter and not have the word, ſo the letter is not it.</p>
            <p>That one may have the letter and not have the word is plaine, <hi>John</hi> 5. 38, 39.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jewes</hi> had the Scriptures, and Chriſt bids them ſearch them, and they thought to have eternall life in them, yet Chriſt tells them they had not the word.</p>
            <p>So the letter cannot be the word which one may have and yet not have the word.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever hath the word hath life, but ſo hath not all who have the letter.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever hath the word hath God, but ſo have not all who have the letter.</p>
            <p>The word is without beginning or without ending, but ſo is not the letter.</p>
            <p>That which can be changed by men is not the word, but the letter is and hath been changed by men, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 25.</p>
            <p>The word of the Lord came to ſuch as had the letter, and ſome of them received it and ſome received it not, yet all had the letter and believed it: All that hear the word it quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, but many hear the letter but are ſtill dead, in ſin. And ſuch they are who know not to diſtinguiſh between the word it ſelfe and the letter which is the declaration thereof, which letter the Devill and wicked men get to plead againſt the word, and for their ſins, which is the great uſe the letter is wreſted to at this day; let any of the ſervants of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove ſin in the word of the Lord, and preſently the Serpent gets a Scripture to plead for it, and ſo to give God the lye, which was his work before the letter was, to wit, to oppoſe the word, in open lying, but now hath got the letter to hide
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168378:8"/> him, and can now come as boldly (with, <hi>it is written) Luke</hi> 4. 10. to uphold his ſin and imperfection, as ever he did with his lye to <hi>Eve,</hi> to ſet up his kingdome of ſin and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection at the firſt, which then he got in by ſubtilty without Scripture, but now by the letter would maintaine it by force, and if any believe to attaine that eſtate againe, before he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, with boldneſſe from the letter he will prove him an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, and find Scripture to murther him for it alſo, he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving but power, to doe it, and this is the uſe the Scriptures are of when ſuch give meanings of them and preach them whoſe eye he hath blinded and have not the word, in them, from which the Scriptures came, and without which none know them nor underſtand them: And thus the Jewiſh Rabbies put Chriſt to death by the letter, <hi>John</hi> 19. 7. And ſo doth he ſuffer to this day in whom ever he is, by the worlds Teachers wreſting the letter; therefore ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> ſuch wreſt all Scriptures to their own diſtruction, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
            <p>And this is the ground of the Devills envy againſt the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light at this day, becauſe we exhort people to the Spirit of Chriſt, and to his light to enlighten their mindes, that they may not read without underſtanding, and ſo wreſt the Scriptures to their own deſtruction, which things we our ſelves did while we was in our fallen wiſdome, for while man is in darkneſſe the beſt of Gods gifts are perverted to a wrong end, but being enlightned from the word, the gift is ſeen and ſanctified to its right end, without which it cannot, for God hath placed the bleſſing and right uſe of all his mercies in his Son, who is the light of the world, the word by which all was made and is upholden, therefore is he firſt to be preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who is firſt and laſt, to enlighten people that ſit in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, death, and deluſion, which light being firſt received, all the gifts of God are yea and amen therein to his praiſe and the creatures good, for without faith all is loſt, and it is not faith in the gift, that ſaves, but faith in the giver, for many did believe in the Scripture, and thought to have eternall life therein but could not believe in the light of the vvorld, and ſo denyed the giver, and the Scriptures could not ſave theſe,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168378:9"/> but in their thoughts thereof deceived themſelves, who had not the word in them, and ſo ſtuck in the letter, but would not come to the light of life, for it is he that hath the Son hath life, and not every one that hath the letter, and ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone have the word of life, which ſuch as ſtick in the letter knows not nor can hear, <hi>John</hi> 8. 47.</p>
            <p>Nay there was many that heard Chriſt ſpeak, but did not nor could they hear the word, <hi>John</hi> 8. 43. And this was much more then the letter, yet ſuch blind and deaf creatures being blinded by the God of this world, they thought to have eternall life in the Scripture. Saith Chriſt <hi>v. 47. He that is of God heareth Gods words, ye therefore hear them not, becauſe ye are not of God;</hi> yet did Chriſt ſpeak the words of God, and they did hear him carnally (as carnall men doe the letter) and could make him anſwer to his ſpeech, but could not hear the words of God, as Chriſt plainly ſaith, and here thou maiſt read thy blindneſſe.</p>
            <p>Alſo that place <hi>Acts</hi> 17. which you think makes ſo much for you to prove the letter the word, it doth but fall on your own heads, as all other Scriptures doe, for them of <hi>Berea</hi> was not called more noble then them of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> becauſe they had the Scriptures read, for the <hi>Jews</hi> of <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> had the Scriptures read every Sabbath day, but this was their nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in that they received the word gladly with all readineſſe of mind, and then ſearched the Scriptures dayly; firſt they received the word to enlighten, and then ſearched the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the light: ſo this doth plainly prove that they had not the word before, though they had Scripture before, ſo that here you doe but prove that the letter is not the word: Alſo this place clearly proves that one may have the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures all their lives, and read them in way of worſhip con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly (for ſo did both theſe ſorts of <hi>Jewes</hi>) and yet neither know word nor Scriptures untill they received the word of light; but when the word is received, or not received, that makes the difference of believers, and unbelievers, the one owns, the other envies and perſecute though both have the Scriptures; this Scripture proves this in the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and your practice proves the ſame in you <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who call your ſelves
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168378:9"/> Chriſtians, who are found joyning with the lewd people, as they did, and ſtirring up their minds to perſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e through your lyes, which otherwiſe might be ſilent, ſo your worke is ſeene, and makes it manifeſt what word you know, as all thy yes and ſlanders in thy booke, may teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fie thee to be one of that envious broode, which is the moſt they ſerve for, for us they touch not, yet is thy reward no leſſe, yet this all may note that the ſearching of the Scriptures without the word firſt received, cannot find the way to faith, as this ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth plainly prove, for till the eye be opened with the light of the word of life, The Scriptures are a myſtery to the Carnall underſtanding, and all that man can doe with them in that ſtate is to wreſt them to his own deſtruction, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 16. And you who are Judging of Scriptures, and ſetting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſo to doe, without the light of Chriſt, are they who lead the blind, and reſiſt the holy Spirit, as did your fathers ſo doe you, reſiſt the Spirit with your Imaginations from the letter. Be aſhamed of your doctrine, hath the Spirit given out the letter to teſtifie of the light of the world and its ſuffic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cy, and that there is no other way out of the world but Chriſt the light of the world, and that the light &amp; the way are one. And doe you pervert this againſt the light to prove it not ſufficient?</p>
            <p>Hath God given his Word to his ſeede in every generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and hath promiſed that it ſhall never depart out of the mouth of that ſeede for ever, <hi>Iſa:</hi> 59. 21. By which Word all was made, and all his are to be guided and ſanctified; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the teſtimony of ſome few of thoſe who had this Word is in writing, to witneſſe that Chriſt is this Word, and that all are to waite for him. And will you take this letter, and pervert it againſt this Word, to ſet it in its ſtead, to keepe from this Word, and call it the Word which doth but declare of the Word? now is the deceipt of your high notion found out, who have pretended ſo much light and Spirit, that now the true light is come, and the gift of the Spirit is manifeſt for every one to profit withall, you are found the greateſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and ſet your ſelves to make the people evill-affected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light and Spirits teachings, though no man can ſay
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168378:10"/> that Jeſus is Lord, but by that Spirit which is given to every one to profit withall, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12. 3. 7. And all your prayers and worſhips that are out of this light and before it, are blind and abominable. And all you prove in this your oppoſing the light and Word, is but your ſelves Children of darkneſſe and wholy Ignorant of the Spirits teaching, and the leaſt Child of light ſhall Judge you herein, for the leaſt that ever knew any thing from God, eyther of Judgement, teaching, or promiſe, or power, they know they have it in Spirit, and ſuch know that what the Saints declare of in the letter which they received of God in Spirit, will not ſatisfie their longing ſoules, unleſſe they can have it from God in Spirit alſo; ſo that your oppoſing the ſpirituall light and power, doth but give occaſion to all that have the leſt ſight of the Spirit, and its teaching, to ſee you heart blind, and ſo joyning with the God of this world to blind the minds of others alſo, and the leaſt of the Children of light, can you not deceive with this, onely you diſcover your <hi>Babel</hi> which you have builded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the light and Spirit, in your Imaginations from the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, without the light, the ground of all the falſe worſhips, ſects, opinions, and deviſions. The ſeate of the hypocrite, and Court of Conceites, in which you bleſſe your ſelves in darkneſſe without God in the world, not having the Father and the Son in you, and ſo are out of the doctrine of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of <hi>John</hi> 9. 10. And ſo are ſhut out of the habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Children of light. O blind men, how hath your wiſdome perverted you, and the Devill deceived you? Is this the doctrine of Chriſt, that his light is not ſufficient to lead without ſomething elſe joyned with it? That the Spirit is falſe and erroneous that bids take heed to a light within, <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 35? And that Chriſt did not Commend people to a light within? Is this the doctrine of Chriſt, That men are not led into all truth by a light within them, <hi>John</hi> 16. 13. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8. 14? That to ſuppoſe that God in men is their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher is an error, <hi>John 6. 45. John 14. 26. John</hi> 17, 23? That to declare the light within is another report and another Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? That its an error to ſay that Chriſt is in the Saints in their ſufferings ſuffering with them, <hi>Acts 9 5. 2 Cor:</hi> 1. 5.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168378:10"/> 
               <hi>Colo:</hi> 1. 24? That its an error to ſay that is the true light, even the light of the world that lighteth every man that comes into the world, and that it alone is ſufficient, <hi>Joh: 1. 9. John</hi> 8. 12. And that the light of the world is the onely way, which leads to all other things, but no other thing can lead to it, but it ſelfe? <hi>John 14. 6. John</hi> 8. 12. And much more ſuch like doctrine, the man of ſin is not afraid to preach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, thereby to deny the light of Chriſt to be ſufficient, leaſt that light ſhould reveale him all againſt the doctrine of Chriſt. And that he may not be ſuſpected to be the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and man of ſin, who is thus oppoſing Chriſt, and plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſin; you would perſwade us that the Antichriſt will but be one ſingle perſon when he comes; That ſo while peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are looking for him in a ſingle perſon, he may thus op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the light and ſpirituall appearance of Chriſt in his Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands and ten thouſands, who are gathered as the ſand of the Sea for multitude, to oppoſe the light and plead for ſinne. And to confound your ſelves, you ſay againe that even now are there many Antichriſts, but cannot ſee your ſelves to be they, who are armeing your ſelves thus againſt his light and appearance, and as one of his laſt ſhifts, to ſet the letter in his ſtead, which doth but declare of his appearance who is the light of the world, made manifeſt to enlighten them that ſit in darkneſſe, and deſtroy the workes of the Devill, in all that beleeve and follow him.</p>
            <p>And where this light is received and followed, you are therewith Comprehended, your worke and the end of it, and in all that you doe in thus oppoſing the light of the world, you are but breaking your ſelves againſt the Corner Stone, fooliſh women who are pulling downe your own houſe with your owne hands, for the more you reſiſt the light the more it ſhines, and the more you Raile againſt the light and Spirit, the more you are manifeſt to be out of the doctrine of Chriſt, who is that light and Spirit, and you doe but give an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to all that ſee your worke, to ſee the Innocency of that light you oppoſe, and to ſee you ſet againſt that which is the onely thing teſtified of in the Scriptures, and ſo ſhall that in every tender Conſcience witneſſe againſt you, and for that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168378:11"/> Spirit you reſiſt. So behold your doctrine, and compare it with the Apoſtles, and with Chriſts, and the Prophets, and let that of God in your conſcience g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve righteous Judgement upon you, if this of yours be the doctrine of Chriſt, had <hi>John</hi> ſaid concerning Chriſt, <hi>This is the true light that li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hteth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that cometh into the world;</hi> but it is not ſufficient with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſomething elſe, had he been a forerunner of Chriſt? or of ſomething elſe? Had Chriſt ſaid I am the light of the world, beleeve in the light and follow it, but it is not ſufficient with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſomething elſe with it, for it is but a naturall light; had not he then taught them a naturall foundation in ſtead of a ſpirituall, who ſaid beleeve in the light, that you may be the Chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dren of light; had the Apoſtles gone forth to preach Chriſt the light for every one to beleeve in, &amp; ſaid, this is our meſſage wee have received of God and declare unto you, that God is light, and whatſoever makes manifeſt is light, and all things that are made manifeſt are reproved by the light, but this light is not ſufficient, had they then preached Chriſt all in all, a ſole ground and authour of faith; nay had they not been mad-men that would have beleeved them, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had thus preached as you doe, a light and Spirit but not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. Had the Prophets preached a Covenant of light <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to beleeve, and when they had done told them that it was not ſufficient without the letter, had not they deſtroyed their faith in their generation before the letter was written; nay goe through all the Scriptures and find any of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light in your doctrine if you can till then for ſhame ceaſe calling us <hi>deceived and deceiving Quakers;</hi> many of us have been too long deceived with ſuch blind guides, enemies to the light, who have alwayes reſiſted the Spirit but the light hath appeared and is received, by which we ſee the deceivers, and no more by them can wee be deceived: neither can Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt cover himſelfe in the letter, whoſe worke is to devoure the light and Spirit that gave it forth, it will not ſerve your turne whoſe end is contrary, that which was given forth to teſtifie of the light of the world will never ſay it's not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; and that which ſaith he is the authour and finiſher, you cannot make it ſay there muſt be ſomething before him, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168378:11"/> that which ſaith hee is all in all will not limit him; and that which ſaith the Spirit giveth life the ſame ſaith the letter kills; ſo behold your work and be aſhamed, ſuch dead deceitfull blind doctrine, is ſutable to ſuch dead workes you bring forth and darke wayes you walke in; the Children of light ſees you, whoſe faces are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from you and are ſet out of the world, in which your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſtands conformable to it: and in vaine doth <hi>Pharaoh</hi> purſue, or <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aleck</hi> ſmite the hindmoſt it is but that you may be drown'd in your envy, and with the floods of your own confuſion, that thereby your names may be blotted out and become a curſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord and his people, for all your envy and hard ſpeeches you have ſpoken againſt the truth, ſlanders and falſe accuſations you caſt upon the ſervants thereof; though wee have not deſired this evill da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to come upon you by perſiſting in your wickednes, the Lord he knoweth, and for the abominable lyes thou haſt caſt upon us in thy booke, wee are content to beare them, being no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing then our portion in this world, yet that thou haſt ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them falſely, every day ſhall make them more manifeſt. And this I ſhall ſay unto them all, before all the world, if the Lord our righteouſneſſe, whoſe righteouſneſſe we ſerve in ſoule and ſpirit, doe not cleare us thereof by a godly converſation, then paper and inck will not; ſo to the Lord and into the hands of his power we referre our ſelves therein.</p>
            <p>And this I ſay as of the Scriptures, God is at liberty to ſpeake to his people by them if he pleaſe, and where they are given by inſpiration he doth ſo, and ſo is he at liberty to ſpeake by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther created thing, as to <hi>Balaam</hi> by his Aſſe, or by his owne Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate voyce; but of him I have learned to know his word, from that he ſpeakes by, and not to limit him, though you have not. And this I ſay further, that men may read the Scriptures in the booke without, all their time, and till the eye and eare be opened within, with the light of Chriſt, they cannot heare the words of God in the Scriptures, no nor from Chriſt himſelfe were he in the fleſh his owne words ſhall be my witneſſe herein, <hi>John</hi> 8. 47. and your practiſes prove it dayly.</p>
            <p>ANd now a word to thy brother, in the latter part of thy book, whoſe work is to clear the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> from being the Antichriſt, and that the man of ſin, and the Antichriſt will but be a ſingle perſon; ſuch a work as none of the men of God ever
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168378:12"/> undertook, but the children muſt plead for their Mother; And yet in thy pleading for her, leaſt thou ſhould injure the kingdom of the man of ſin, the Antichriſt, thou firſt puts it out of queſtion, that none needs to fear him come already, they may ſleep quietly for that, and when he doth come he will be but a ſingle man, ſo none thats now alive needs fear in the leaſt that they are he, for ſayeſt thou he will be but one man: thus haſt thou cleared the world of the man of ſin, and the Antichriſt for the preſent, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee thy ſelfe to be he who art pleading for his kingdome till dooms day (as people call it) in thy 76 page: And who art lying againſt the holy Ghoſt, ſaying that Antichriſt will be but one man, and that he is not yet come, contradicting the Spirit of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>even now there are many Antichriſts, 1 John</hi> 2. 18. So thou art the Antichriſt who art the lyar, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 22. And ſaith the Spirit, he is Antichriſt who denyes the Father and the Son; ſo thy companion is one who ſaith, To ſuppoſe God in men to teach them is an error, p. 17. thus he denyes the Father to be his onely Teacher; And thou art another, who calls it an error to preach up the Spirit of Chriſt within for a Teacher, p. 68. and calls it an evill Spirit, and herein thou denies the Son; and many ſuch An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts there are in the world who both deny the Father and the Son, for he that denyes the one denyes both, and he is an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt that ſo doth; and no new thing it is to the children of light to ſee ſuch who have received the ſpirit of the world in their hearts, to deny the Father and Son there to teach and lead, and theſe was the Antichriſts <hi>John</hi> ſaw who was gone out into the world, and ſo the Spirit of God and of the world could not both be confeſſed in one heart, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. but where the Spirit that was of God is, there Chriſt is confeſſed in heart, and God alſo, but who hath corrupted his ways, ſaith in his heart, There is no God, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 14. 1. So try thy wayes, and try thy words, who denies Chriſt within, and calls it teaching up the Spirit of Chriſt apart from his body, to preach Chriſt within, and ſayes its an evill Spirit, to ſay Chriſt is in them, and thus the Reprobate who knows not Chriſt in thee art become a Teacher, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. Haſt thou not here ſhewed thy ſelfe the Antichriſt indeed, who thus oppoſes Chriſt in his Saints; Doth not he ſay, <hi>Without me you can doe nothing, abide in me and I in you, he that abideth in me and I in him the ſame bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>, forth much fruit, for without me you can do nothing, Joh.</hi> 15, 4, 5.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168378:12"/> Doth not Chriſt ſay to the Father (touching the Saints) <hi>I in them and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one,</hi> John 17. 23. Did Chriſt here preach up his Spirit apart from his body? Or was this an evil Spirit, and a Spirit of error as thou ſays it is in us? And did not all his Miniſters preach the ſame? Doth not <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, <hi>when it pleaſed the father to reveal his Son in me that I might preach him,</hi> Gal. 1. 16. <hi>And Chriſt in you the hope of glory whom we preach,</hi> Col. 1. 27. <hi>And know ye not that Chriſt is in you except you be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates,</hi> 2 Cor. 13. 5. <hi>My little children of whom I travell in birth againe till Chriſt be formed in you,</hi> Gal. 4. 19. <hi>And he that hath the Son hath life, and he that hath not the Son hath not life,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 12. <hi>And he that abideth in the Doctrine of Chriſt hath both the Father and the Son, If any come and bring not that Doctrine receive them not, nor bid them God ſpeed, 2 John</hi> 10, 11. And was this an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Spirit in all theſe, and many more too much to ſet down here? Or did they preach Chriſt apart from his body, as thou chargeſt us for the ſame teſtimony we bear now? Or were this good in them, and is it an error in us to witneſſe the ſame? O how is the hidden things of <hi>Eſau</hi> found out; are they not blind indeed who cannot ſee Antichriſt now revealing, and who he is that denies the Father and the Son, thy work and thy brothers in this book, and many ſuch Antichriſts there are in the world, that deny Chriſt come in the fleſh, and now the light reveals you, what Spirits you are of; Is all your talking of Chriſt come to this, that if any confeſſe him, it is called an evil Spirit, and an error, and out of your Synagogues muſt be caſt: Was there ever ſuch a blind generation, who have denyed the light, the Spirit, the Father, and the Son, and now deny the letter alſo, that any ſhould own what is in it declared, further then to talk on? Is it not time for all you that loves your ſouls to come out from amongſt theſe blind men, who thus reſiſt the Spirit, and thus blaſpheme God in his Temple, even in the bodies of his Saints, calling him an evill Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 16, 17. This blind do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine may ſerve to keep your ſelves in your imaginations, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the children of light it can doe no hurt, with the light are you comprehended, and all your dark airy Spirits, the Shepheard is in his flock, its too late to tell us its a deluſion, neither can you hide Antichriſt nor the man of ſin any longer, you are ſeen many Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts who denies Chriſt, but who hath received the Chriſt the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted, and have the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ction in them knows all things, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168378:13"/> you nor your mother can be hid, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he that hath begot you, thus to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inſt Chriſt in his Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſh and be aſhamed you b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſee you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> confuſion and ſtop your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, doſt not thou in thy 69 p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge after thou have c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lled it an evill ſpirit a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d an error to wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſe Chriſt within, and ſaid it was to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>each him apart from his body, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye.</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſayeſt thou Chriſt doth dwell in their hearts by faith, but note <hi>(ſayeſt thou)</hi> that faith is the ſubſtance of the thing hoped for, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſo being by faith thou wouldſt make people believe its not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eally ſo, but ſome imagination or thought of a thing to come, and yet ſayes, faith is the ſubſtance of the thing hoped for. Alſo p 78. where thou art pleading for the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> not to be the Antichriſt, thy argument i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> confeſſeth Chriſt come in the fleſh, ſo thou haſt proved the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> to be of God, for ſaith <hi>John</hi> expreſly, <hi>Every ſpirit that confeſſeth Christ is come in the fleſh is of God, 1 John</hi> 4 2. ſo thou haſt w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proved for thy mother, if any b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo blind as to believe thee, but where Chriſt is appeared her confeſſion is ſeen to be like her children, who ſay he came 16 hundred years ſince, but if any confeſſe him come now in them, ſhe and her brood would mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>her them, but but if all be of God who thus confeſſe him, then who is not, for I never yet met with any that did not: Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> confeſſion little hurts the man of ſin or his kingdome in your hearts, one that confeſſeth the life of Chriſt made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in mortall fleſh, doth more trouble the Devil's kingdome, then all the Whores confeſſion and his children ever ſince the myſtery of in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y came in; and therefore it is that this confeſſion is death to her and her children, and the man of ſin hath all h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s up againſt it where it is, and this is the cauſe why all this venome is caſt upon us in your book, but the knowledge of Chriſt in our hearts bears all without trouble, yet ſuch a body of confuſion death and darkneſſe is amongſt you ſince the light of Chriſt appeared, and you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted it as the like hath not been ſeen ſince the world was, eſpecial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y among you who once had ſome tenderneſſe in you, what a wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k is this of yours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all your venome, to undertake to clear <hi>Babylon</hi> of the man of ſin, and of the Antichriſt, nay to clear all the world of him, and ſayes he is not riſen, and ſayes in your 37 page you think the ſixt head of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy did hinder the coming of the man of ſin in <hi>Pauls</hi> time, and ſomething elſe hath hindered him ſince, for he is not riſen yet by your doctrine, but being blinded by him cannot ſee that its he in you that is now uttering all this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion to hide himſelf in your hearts, &amp; in others alſo, by denying Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and ſetting you to look for the man of ſin yet to come, which muſt be one man when he comes, but were you not blind indeed you might look in and ſee from whom it is that all this lying, ſlandering, and confuſion, and wickedneſſe, comes that is ſent out into the world, this comes not from God but from the Devil and man of ſin, which did you ſee, ſhame would ſtop your mouth from being ſo buſie in that you know not on.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
